A Guide to the Papers of Richard Cutts, 1753-1886
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
- CORRESPONDENCE
  - Thomas Todd (1765-1826) to Richard Cutts 1817-1822, 5 ALS
    Reveals concerns about Monroe's appointment of John Quincy Adams and asks him to take care of some financial matters for him Washington (1817 Apr 15); three slaves and his son, Johnson, sick with typhoid fever, caused him to miss the current term of the Supreme Court, although he was anxious about changes in the judicial system (1819 Jan 31); and plans to visit Montpelier on the way home to Frankfurt, Kentucky (1822 Mar 3)
  - Elisha Tracy (1766-1846) to Richard Cutts 1814-1815, 3 ALS
    Writes that the sons of the late Governor Roger Griswold stand accused of "holding direct intercourse with the British squadron" as an example of the treachery going on in Connecticut (1814 Mar 22); asks for help with an appointment (1815 Feb 13); and mentions the mortification of the enemies of the administration of Madison at news of the peace agreement (1815 Mar 20)
  - Charles Turner, Jr. (1760-1839) to Richard Cutts 1814 February & July, 3 ALS
    Discusses political appointments for Massachusetts
  - Marcia Van Ness to Anna Cutts Tuesday morning
    Inquires after her health and asks if there is anything she can do for her in her illness
  - Benjamin Waterhouse (1754-1846) to Abigail Adams [1782?] & 1816, 2 ALS
    Thanks her for her letter and pamphlet, proposes to settle in Boston, and sends his regards to the rest of her family ([1782?] Nov 5); and to Richard Cutts, offers to supply Cutts with a correct list of the newly adopted names of medicines used by the medical staff of the army, for the military supply forms, and complains at his treatment by a young surgeon at the Brownsville Hospital, now supposedly acting as an inspector of medical men and matters at Cambridge and who desires his post (1816)
  - Nathan Weston (1782-1872) to Richard Cutts 1814 April 12
    Approves of the Republican administrations of Jefferson and Madison, congratulates Cutts on his appointment, and discusses the interest of his son, Nathan Weston, Jr., in the appointment of district attorney for Augusta County, Maine
  - Laban Wheaton (1754-1846) to Richard Cutts 1814 April 14
    Supports John Balkam for an appointment in the army
  - Ezekiel Whitman (1776-1866) to Richard Cutts 1813 January 2
    Supports Captain Ebenezer Greenleaf for an appointment as sailing master in the navy
  - William Widgery (1753-1822) to Richard Cutts, 3 ALS
    Discusses troubles with the Embargo in his area of Portland, Maine, suggests using fast sailing schooners to enforce the Embargo, offers to build them for the navy at $4,600 each, and tells a story of a man who informed the collector about a cargo of rum and was tarred and feathered for his trouble (1808 Dec 2 & 24)
  - Levi Woodbury (1789-1851) to Midshipman Walter C. Coles 1832 January 30
    Orders him to New York to report for duty
  - John Woodman to Richard Cutts 1811 January 31
    Discusses an appointment for district attorney in Boston
- MISCELLANEOUS PAPERS
  - Commission for Walter Coles Cutts as Midshipman, signed by John Quincy Adams 1823 March 4
  - Envelopes franked by Dolley Madison 1840, n.d., 14 items
  - Envelope franked by James Madison n.d.
  - Genealogy of the Cutts Family compiled by Cecil Hampden Cutts Howard, with a section on Richard Cutts and Miscellaneous Notes n.d.
  - Invitation from [Lydia Howard] Sigourney to Richard Cutts Tuesday morning
  - Invitation from Dolley Madison to Mary and Richard [Cutts ?] n.d.
  - Letters to Lucia Beverly Cutts (1851-?) concerning her Memoirs and Letters of Dolley Madison, wife of James Madison, President of the U.S.1886, 2 items
  - News clippings 1894, n.d.
  - Oath of Richard Cutts to perform duties of the Superintendent General of Military Supplies of the United States sworn before Joseph Forrest 1813 March 31
  - Obituaries for Colonel Richard D. Cutts, Dr. Harry M. Cutts, and General Richard D. Cutts (1817-1883) 1845, 1883 & n.d.
  - Pew Rent Receipt to Richard Cutts of Saco, Maine 1808 July 20
  - Poem addressed "To the Honorable John Quincy Adams - On Reading his beautiful poem on the Wants of Man. By a Lady" n.d.
  - Printed "Appeal to Graduates and Others" for Biographical Information from John Langdon Sibley, Librarian at Harvard College n.d.
  - Promissory Notes signed by James Madison to Charles J. Nourse 1829 January 27
  - Receipt given to Richard Cutts for part of minister's salary at Kittery, Maine 1753 March 19
  - Silhouette of Martha Jefferson Hackley Cutts n.d.
  - Commission of Richard Cutts as Massachusetts Justice of the Peace, signed by Governor Caleb Strong (1745-1819) 1801 June 12